Register of the George Wolfgang Felix Hallgarten Papers, 1874-1975
Hoover Institution Archives
George Wolfgang Felix Hallgarten Papers,
1874-1975
42013
Hallgarten, George Wolfgang Felix, 1901-
44 manuscript boxes, 2 microfilm reels, 4 phonotapes (18.5 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, diaries, speeches and writings, photocopies of government documents, propaganda leaflets, and printed matter, relating to European diplomacy, imperialism, psychology of national socialism and totalitarianism, U.S. and German propaganda during World War II, and the arms race, 1870-1970. Includes drafts of a study by G. W. F. Hallgarten, entitled Imperialismus vor 1914.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Armaments.; Imperialism.; National socialism.; Propaganda, German.; Psychology.; Totalitarianism--Psychology.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda.; Europe.; Europe--History--1871-1918.; Europe--History--1918-1945.; Germany.
Biographical Note
1901, January 3 Born, Munich, Germany
1925 Ph.D., University of Munich
1928 Published work based on doctoral dissertation, entitled Studien ueber die deutsche Polenfreundschaft 1830-1848 (A study of German-Polish friendship 1830-1848), Munich
1933 Exiled from Germany to France
1935-1936 Lecturer at the École des Hautes Études Sociales et Internationales in Paris
1935 Published excerpt of Vorkriegsimperialismus (Pre-war imperialism), Paris
1937 Immigrated to the United States
1938 Lecturer at Brooklyn College
1939 Private research at Hoover Institution
1940-1941 Research associate in history at the University of California, Berkeley
1941 Married Katherine MacArthur Drew, attorney from San Francisco
1942-1945 Served with the U.S. Army, Combat Intelligence and Psychological Warfare, in Europe
1945-1949 Historian and later senior research analyst for the War Department
1947 Served on a team of the War Crimes Branch to document case against war criminals, Nuernberg
1949-1950 Visiting professor at the University of Munich
1951 Published Imperialismus vor 1914 (Imperialism before 1914), two volumes, Munich
1954 Published Why Dictators? New York
1955 Published Hitler, Reichswehr und Industrie (Hitler, the imperial army and industry), Frankfurt
1955-1956 Co-founder of the American Committee for the Study of War Documents, a microfilming project
1956 Lecture tour sponsored by the University of Minnesota
1957 Published Daemonen oder Retter? (Demons or saviours?), Frankfurt
1958-1959 Lecture tour of the German Federal Republic, research in the archives of the Auswaertiges Amt, Bonn
1963 Published second edition of Imperialismus vor 1914 (Imperialism before 1914), Munich
1965 Lectures at universities in India and Japan
1967 Lectures at universities in Rome and Munich
1967 Published Das Wettruesten (The arms race), Frankfurt
1968-1969 Visiting professor of history, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque
1969 Published Das Schicksal des Imperialismus im 20. Jahrhundert (The fate of imperialism in the twentieth century), Frankfurt
1969 Published Als die Schatten fielen (When the shadows fell), Berlin
1970-1971 Visiting professor, University of Dayton
1971-1972 Visiting professor, University of North Carolina, Charlotte
1974 Published Deutsche Industrie und Politik von Bismarck bis heute (German industry and politics from Bismarck to today), Frankfurt (with Joachim Radkau)
1975, May 22 Died in Washington, D.C.
Series Description
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1936-1975., Box 1
  Curricula vitae, publicity for lectures, personal and professional notices, arranged chronologically by topic
- SUBJECT FILE, 1874-1974., Boxes 1-8
  Various pamphlets, newspaper clippings, photocopies of German government documents, mimeographed and printed material, typescripts, handwritten transcripts and bibliographies, correspondence, and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by subject
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1937-1975., Boxes 9-29
  Books, lectures and articles, research proposals, film scripts and synopses, arranged by genre and thereafter alphabetically by title, or if untitled by subject
- MICROFILM., 2 reels (Microfilm cabinet)
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1936-1975
  - Biographical sketches and lists of publications, arranged chronologically (Box 1)
  - Hallgarten family circle. Newspaper clippings and notices, arranged chronologically
  - Hallgarten in Paris, 1935. Reference in book by Maximilian Scheer, So war es in Paris. Photocopy
  - Letters of reference, 1936-1939. Mimeographed copies
  - Announcements for public lectures, 1939-1958, arranged chronologically. Printed copies
  - Letter of appreciation from General Telford Taylor for Hallgarten's assistance in Nuernberg Trials. Conveyed by Col. Edward H. Young, July 22, 1947
  - Washington Research Consultants, 1955. Professional announcements. Printed copies
  - Letters to Mrs. George W. F. Hallgarten, sent while on lecture tour sponsored by the University of Minnesota, February 14 to May 13, 1956 (12)
  - Memorabilia of Minnesota lecture tour, 1956
  - Lecture tour of Germany 1958-1959. Newspaper announcements, invitations, schedule, arranged chronologically
  - Lecture tour of India, November 1965. Correspondence and itinerary
  - Lecture tour of Japan, November -December 1965. Schedules, invitations, and miscellaneous papers
  - Miscellany. Typescript notes
- SUBJECT FILE, 1874-1974
  - Alexan, G. F., 1969. Newspaper article by Alexan on Africa with personal note by author to Hallgarten (Box 1)
  - Alldeutscher Verband (Pan-Germanism). Typescript notes in German and English, photocopies of minutes of meetings held in 1896-1900, dissertation by Willi Krebs, entitled "Der Alldeutsche Verband in den Jahren 1918-1939"
  - American Committee for the Study of War Documents (Box 2)
    - General
      - Establishment of the Committee. Reports. Typescripts and reprint
      - "Memorandum on the Organization and Purpose of the Committee," n.d. Typescript and corrections, two mimeographed drafts
      - "Draft of Constitution and By-Laws," n.d. Two photocopies
      - Membership list. Typescript and mimeographed copies
      - Ford Foundation grant, 1955 (?). Typescript draft of application, newspaper announcement of grant, mimeographed announcement
      - Agendas and minutes of meetings, 1955-1957. Mimeographed and typescript copies
      - Lists of seized German documents, 1954-1955. Three mimeographed lists
      - Memorandum on the preparation of a new guide to captured German documents, n.d. Typescript and mimeographed copies
      - Reports, 1955-1957
      - Miscellany. Clippings and holographic notes
    - Correspondence
      - 1955
      - 1956
      - 1956, with Horst Drechsler
      - 1956, with university libraries
      - 1957
      - 1958-1960
    - Highlights of findings, n.d., n.t., by Robert Wolfe. Typescript
  - Bagdad Railroad and the German military mission in Turkey, 1891-1914. Photocopies and handwritten transcripts of German diplomatic documents (Box 3)
  - Bagdad Railroad in Bulgaria, 1883-1892. Photocopies of German diplomatic documents
  - Columbians, 1946. Newspaper clippings
  - Diplomatic archives. Pamphlet
  - Disarmament and the arms race. Miscellaneous newspaper clippings and pamphlets
  - Education. Newspaper clippings and pamphlet
  - European government and politics, 1950 (?). Mimeographed reading lists
  - Fischer (Fritz) controversy on the origins of World War I, 1964-1969. Holographic notes, articles by colleagues, newspaper clippings
  - France. Newspaper clippings
  - Germany
    - Commerce with Morocco, 1904-1905. Photocopies of German diplomatic documents
    - Diplomatic history. Pamphlets on German relations with France, Poland, and Sweden
    - Diplomatic relations with China, 1898-1900. Photocopies of handwritten transcripts of German diplomatic documents
    - Economic situation after World War II. Pamphlets
    - Military mission to Turkey, 1891-1898. Photocopies of German diplomatic documents
    - News reports of April 16, 1945. Carbon copies of typescripts in German
    - Political events of the 1950s to 1970s. Newspaper clippings and pamphlets (Box 4)
  - Himmler, Heinrich. Magazine clippings and photocopy of invitation to the young Himmler from Hallgarten as a child to a garden party
  - Historiography. Miscellaneous announcements of interest to historians. Printed copies and newspaper clippings
  - Hitler's reception for the Yugoslavian Prime Minister Milan Stajandinovic, January 17, 1938. Photocopy of seating arrangement for state dinner given by the Krupps
  - Hungary. Printed pamphlet and flyer
  - International co-operation. Miscellaneous pamphlets and clippings
  - Institute for Documentary Research on Foreign Nations (Box 5)
    - Prospectus, n.d. Twelve different drafts. Typescript, carbon and mimeographed copies
    - Research program, 1962. Programs for utilizing German and Japanese documents, research ideas for Latin American documents, general lists of possible topics. Typescript, mimeographed and carbon copies
    - Budget, n.d. Typescript and mimeographed budgets
    - Certificate of incorporation, 1961. Two mimeographed copies
    - By-laws, n.d. Four drafts. Mimeographed and carbon copies
    - Information on similar institutes. Printed copies
    - Newspaper publicity, 1961. Article drafts and newspaper clippings
    - Staffing, n.d. Holographic, typescript, and mimeographed copies
    - Recruitment of Board of Trustees, 1962. Lists of names, resumes, correspondence
    - Recruitment of Executive Director, 1962. Resumes, correspondence
    - Recruitment of Treasurer, 1962. Letters of reference, memoranda
    - Recruitment of Research Assistants, 1962-1963. Resumes, letters of reference, correspondence
    - Scholars interested in the Institute, n.d. Handwritten lists of names
    - Program notes for presentation of documentary material at Institute, 1962. Holograph in German
    - "Japan's Occupation of Manchuria in the Light of Captured German and Japanese Documents," March 20, 1962. Lecture delivered by Masao Nishikawa, as opening seminar of Institute. Publicity, draft of announcement, newspaper clippings
    - Development of Institute, 1960-1963. Memoranda to members. Mimeographed and typescript copies
    - General correspondence in support of the Institute, arranged chronologically
      - 1957-1961
      - 1962-1964
    - Fund raising plans, 1961-1962. Mimeographed typescript, and handwritten notes
    - Fund raising appeals to members of the Jewish community in the Washington area, July 28, 1962
    - Applications to foundations. Correspondence, arranged chronologically
      - 1961
      - 1962-1963
    - Negotiations with the University of Pittsburgh, 1963. Correspondence, arranged chronologically (Box 6)
    - Negotiations with the American Historical Association, 1963-1964. Correspondence, typescripts, and carbon copies
    - Finances of the Institute, 1960-1965. Bills, cancelled checks, lists of disbursements, arranged chronologically
    - Miscellany. Holographic notes on Institute
  - Italy. Newspaper clippings, transcript of German diplomatic report from Rome, 1924
  - Japan. Pamphlet and newspaper clippings
  - Krupp sales to Turkey, 1874. Photocopies of German diplomatic documents
  - Media. Newspaper clippings, 1956, and correspondence, 1956-1969
  - Microfilm exchange with Czechoslovakia and United States (proposal), 1963. Correspondence and typescript notes
  - Microfilm exchange with East Germany and United States (proposal), 1960-1962. Selective list of holdings of the Zentralarchiv in Potsdam, memoranda, correspondence, arranged chronologically
  - Microfilming of Weimar newspapers (proposal), 1956-1963. Correspondence, arranged chronologically
  - Mitbestimmung (Co-determination) 1956-1957. Pamphlets
  - National Socialism
    - "Der Reichskanzler spricht in Koeln" (The Imperial Chancellor speaks in Cologne), Frankfurter Zeitung, October 27, 1933
    - Requests for prints of Hitler from Heinrich Hoffman, Reichsbildberichterstatter der NSDAP, 1937-1943. Carbon copies of orders, original bills
    - Testimony against National Socialists, 1965. Printed and carbon copies
    - Miscellany. Newspaper clippings, articles by colleagues
  - Nuernberg Trials, 1947. Military Tribunal's indictment #11 against Ernst von Weizsaecker, Wilhelm Keppler, et al. Mimeographed copy
  - Peace research, 1970. Mimeographed copies of conference papers
  - Penkovsky Papers, 1965. Newspaper clippings
  - Peron, Eva, 1952. Argentine newspaper reports of her death
  - Psychological warfare, 1944-1957. Explanatory letter, American and National Socialist leaflets, interrogation reports, radio scripts, allied and German newspapers. Printed and carbon copies
  - Rabotnicheska Prosveta, September 8, 1950. Newspaper of the Bulgarian Socialist Labor Party
  - Ruhr Valley industry, 1949-1950. Excerpts from the Congressional Record. Printed copies
  - Softas (Turkish theology students). Handwritten transcript of German diplomatic report
  - South East Asia Treaty Organization, 1957. Pamphlets
  - Soviet Union. Pamphlet and newspaper clippings
  - Spain. Short articles by colleagues, newspaper clippings
  - Spiegel affair, 1962. Newspaper clippings
  - Stefl, Max, 1958. Pamphlet
  - Steinberger, Albert Barnes, Col., 1971. Article entitled "The Illusive Colonel" by Robert Buchanan. Photocopy of transcript (Box 8)
  - Third World, 1955-1972. Newspaper clippings and pamphlets
  - Turkish railroads, 1891-1902. Photocopies of German documents
  - Turkish taxation systems, 1905 (?). Photocopy of German diplomatic report
  - United States - Political events, 1959-1971. Pamphlets and newspaper clippings
  - Webb, Arthur. Holdings of personal newspaper library
  - Wendel, de. Book by Louis Launay, 1938. Printed copy
  - World War II. Bibliography on index cards for works written primarily in the 1950s
    - A-L
    - M-Z
  - Young Turks, 1896. Handwritten transcript of German diplomatic report
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1937-1975
  - Books (Box 9)
    - Als die Schatten fielen (When the shadows fell), 1969
      - Chapters 5 and 6 of first draft. Typescript
      - Chapters 7, 8, and 9 of first draft. Typescript
      - Part I of second draft. Annotated transcript
      - Part II of second draft. Annotated transcript
      - Part III of second draft. Annotated typescript
      - Excerpt of work for reading over German radio, September 5, 1969. Westdeutscher Rundfunk. Mimeographed copy in German
      - Interview with Hallgarten for German radio, July 12, 1969, Sender Freies Berlin Typescript in German
      - Reviews, 1969-1971, arranged chronologically. Printed, carbon and photocopies in German
    - Daemonen oder Retter? (Demons or saviours?), 1957 (work based on Why Dictators? 1954, and unpublished manuscript, entitled Soziologie der Diktatur. See below) (Box 10)
      - Publishers's announcements. Printed copies
      - Reviews, 1957-1966, arranged chronologically. Printed, carbon, and photocopies
    - "The Devil's Suicide: World War II: Why and Whither," unpublished, 1942
      - Chapters 1 to 4. Typescript
      - Synopses of chapters 5 and 7. Two typescript drafts and carbon copy
      - Chapter 8. Typescript
    - "From Imperialism to Super-State Rivalry," unpublished
      - Reports from recipients of grants from the Penrose Fund, 1940-1941. Printed copies
      - First draft entitled "From Imperialism to Super-Imperialism: The Economic and Social Secrets of World Politics, 1870-1940" (1940?). Annotated typescript
      - Second draft entitled "From Imperialism to Super-Imperialism: The Driving Forces Behind the Screen of European Power Politics, 1870-1940," 1940. Typescript
        - Part I
        - Part II
        - Incomplete carbon copies
      - Third draft entitled "From Imperialism to Super-Imperialism: Changes in the Ideological and Socio-Economic Structure of European Power Politics, 1870-1940," 1941. Annotated typescript (Box 11)
        - Chapters 1 to 3. Typescript
        - Chapters 2 and 3. Incomplete carbon copy
        - Chapter 4. Typescript
      - Fourth draft entitled "Whither Imperialism? The Big Powers and the Colonial World, 1870-1958," 1958(?). Annotated typescript
        - Part I
        - Part II
    - Fifth draft, 1959 (?), n.t. Typescript fragments (Box 12)
      - Part I. Incomplete carbon copy
      - Part IIIA. Typescript
      - Part IIIB. Typescript
    - Sixth draft entitled "Whither Imperialism? The Big Powers and the Colonial World, 1870-1960: A Brief Historical Analysis" (1960?). Typescript
      - Part I. Incomplete carbon copy
      - Part II. Typescript
      - Part II. Carbon copy
      - Part IIIA. Typescript
      - Part IIIA. Carbon copy (Box 13)
      - Part IIIB. Typescript
      - Part IIIB. Carbon copy
      - Epilogue. Annotated typescript
      - Epilogue. Carbon copy of revised typescript
    - Seventh draft entitled "From Imperialism to Super-State Rivalry: The Big Powers and the Colonial World Since the Late 1860s: A Brief Historical Analysis of a Hundred Years of Change," 1967(?). Typescript.
      - Part I
    - Eighth draft entitled "From Imperialism to Super-State Rivalry: A Brief Historical Analysis of a Hundred Years of Change," 1968 (?). Part I
      - Typescript
      - Carbon copy (Box 14)
    - Synopses, n.d. Four drafts in German and English. Carbon copy of transcript
    - Bibliography, n.d. Typescript and holographic notes
    - Research notes. Holographic and typescript notes in German and English
      - Part I
      - Part II
      - Part III
    - Newspaper clippings for research on imperialism
  - "History of the Subversive Movements in the United States Since World War I," unpublished, 1954. With John C. Metcalf. Carbon copy of transcript fragment, two copies of agreement between the authors (typescript of rough draft and carbon copy of revised typescript)
  - Hitler, Reichswehr und Industrie (Hitler, the Imperial Army and Industry), 1955 and 1962 (Box 15)
    - Publisher's announcements. Printed copies
    - Reviews of the first edition, 1954-1959, arranged chronologically. Printed and photocopies
    - Excerpt for reading over German radio, October 24, 1962, Westdeutscher Rundfunk. Mimeographed copy
    - Reviews of the second edition, 1962-1970, arranged chronologically. Printed and photocopies
    - "Memorandum," 1972, in German. Response to critique in Faschismus und Kapitalismus in Deutschland by Henry A. Turner. Carbon copy of typescript
    - Research notes for first essay of work, entitled "Stinnes, Seeckt und Hitler"
    - Research notes for second essay in work, entitled "Hitler und die deutsche Schwerindustrie" (Hitler and German Heavy Industry)
  - Imperialismus vor 1914 (Imperialism before 1914), 1951 and 1963 (Box 16)
    - "Vorkriegsimperialismus" (Pre-War imperialism), 1933. Typescript bound in four volumes
      - Volume I
      - Volume II
      - Volume III (Box 17)
      - Volume IV
      - Notes relating to the writing and microfilming of the original manuscript, n.d. Carbon copy of typescript
      - Reviews of popular excerpt, also entitled Vorkriegsimperialismus, 1935. Photocopy and typescript
    - First edition, 1951
      - Volume I, Part I. Unbound, printed fascicles
      - Volume I, Part II. Unbound, printed fascicles
      - Publisher's announcements. Printed copies (Box 18)
      - Reviews of first edition, 1951-1953
      - Newspaper and journal clippings pasted in note book in roughly chronological order
      - Transcript of letter from Albert Einstein, October 31, 1951, praising the work. Three carbon copies of typescript
    - "Anti-Kritik: Franz Borkenau und mein Werk Imperialismus vor 1914," n.d. Hallgarten's response to critique. Carbon copy of typescript in German
    - Second edition, 1963
      - Publisher's announcements. Printed copies
      - Reviews of second edition, 1962-1966, arranged chronologically
      - Newspaper and journal clippings
      - Research notes, n.d. Typescript in German
  - Das Schicksal des Imperialismus im 20. Jahrhundert (The fate of imperialism in the twentieth century), 1969
    - "Le choc des imperialismes" (The clash of the imperialisms), 1962. Excerpt of chapter from L'Europe du XIXe et du XXe siècle (Europe in the nineteenth and twentieth century) used as basis for the first essay of the work entitled "Der Zusammenprall der Imperialismen im Jahre 1914" (The clash of imperialisms in the year 1914). Printed copy
    - Fritz Fischer und seine Gegner" (Fritz Fischer and his opponents), n.d. Holographic draft of second essay in work. See below
    - "Deutsche Selbstschau nach 50 Jahern: Fritz Fischer, seine Gegner und Vorlaeufer" (German self-appraisal after 50 years: Fritz Fischer, his opponents and predecessors), 1969. Annotated typescript of second essay
    - "The Fate of Imperialism after World War II," 1965. Lecture delivered in Japan, used as basis for third essay "Vom Imperialismus zum Wettkampf der Ueberstaaten" (From imperialism to the rivalry of the super-states). Typescript
    - "Le sort de l'impérialisme du XXe siecle" (The fate of imperialism in the twentieth century), April 4, 1967. Lecture delivered at the Città Universitaria, Rome. Typescript and carbon copy of lecture, invitation, and newspaper review. Basis for third essay in work
    - "I destini dell'imperialismo nel XX secolo, 1967. Direct translation of the above lecture from French into Italian. Mimeographed copy
    - "Vom Imperialismus zum Wettkampf der Ueberstaaten: Die Grossmaechte und die Kolonialwelt seit 1870" (From imperialism to the rivalry of the super-states: The big powers and the colonial world since 1870), 1967. Revised German version of Rome lecture (see above) used as basis for third essay. Typescript, mimeographed copy for reading over German radio (June 20, 1967, Hessischer Rundfunk), and holographic notes (Box 19)
    - "Das Schicksal des Imperialismus im zwanzigsten Jahrhundert: Drei Abhandlungen ueber Kriegsursachen in Vergangenheit und Gegenwart" (The fate of imperialism in the twentieth century: Three essays about the origins of war in the past and present), 1967. Rough draft for preface of the work. Carbon copy of typescript
    - Reviews, 1969-1971, arranged chronologically
  - "Superman: Rise and Fall of Would-Be Aristocrats: Studies in Political Psycho-Pathology," unpublished, 1946
    - First draft, 1946
      - Chapters 1 and 2. Typescript
      - Chapters 3 and 4. Typescript
      - Chapters 5 to 9. Typescript
    - "Uebermensch: Aufstieg und Fall von moechtegern Aristokraten: Politische psycho-pathologische Studien," 1946. Literal translation of first draft into German by the author. Fragmentary carbon copy of typescript and holograph
    - Second draft, 1948
      - Chapters 1 and 2. Typescript
      - Chapters 1 and 2. Carbon copy
      - Chapters 3 and 4. Typescript (Box 20)
      - Chapters 3a. Incomplete carbon copy
      - Chapters 5 to 9. Typescript
      - Chapters 5 to 9. Fragmentary carbon copy
  - Das Wettruesten: Seine Geschichte bis zur Gegenwart (The arms race: Its history up to the present), 1967
    - Published German version
      - Publisher's announcements. Printed copies
      - Excerpt for reading over German radio, July 17, 1967, Westdeutscher Rundfunk. Mimeographed copy
      - Reviews, 1967-1969, arranged chronologically
      - Newspaper clippings and photocopies
    - Unpublished English version